A Guide to the Carter Perkins, Jr. Papers, 1893-1926
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Carter Perkins, Jr. Papers, 1893-1926
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1960-004
0.5 cu. ft. 1 box
Papers of Carter Perkins, Jr., a student at Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College (now Virginia Tech) in the 1890s and resident of Newport News, Virginia. Includes university catalog of 1894-1895, school annuals (The Bugle) of 1895 and 1898, photographs, and fundraising literature for the construction of War Memorial Hall. Also includes two business account books, probably used by Perkins for bookkeeping coursework.
Perkins, Carter, Jr.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Carter Perkins, Jr. Papers were acquired by Newman Library in two accruals in 1960 and 1961.
Biographical Note
Carter Perkins, Jr. was born in Virginia on August 12, 1861. The son of Carter and Mary M. Graves Perkins, he was living with his parents in Charles City County, Virginia in 1870. By 1880, the family had moved to New Kent County, and Perkins is described there as a 17-year-old sawyer, probably working for his father, whose occupation is listed as "sawmill man." In addition to his other activities, the elder Perkins apparently worked as a dentist and had business and banking interests.
Carter Perkins, Jr. of Newport News, Virginia is listed as a special student in both the 1892/1893 and 1893/1894 catalogs of the Virginia Agricultural & Mechanical College (now Virginia Tech). The 1894/1895 catalog lists him as a sophomore.
By 1900, Perkins was living in Newport News with the family of his sister, Mary M. Lett, and her husband, attorney Ralph M. Lett. At the time, Perkins was employed as a clerk at a furniture company. Perkins seems to have remained a bachelor and continued to live with his sister's family. In the 1920 census, he was described as a self-employed salesman but had retired by 1930. Carter Perkins Jr. died on December 8, 1935.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains the papers of Carter Perkins, Jr., a student at Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College (now Virginia Tech) during the 1890s and a resident of Newport News, Virginia. The collection consists largely of memorabilia relating to Perkins's college years, including the 1894/1895 VAMC catalog, copies of the 1895 and 1898 editions of the school's annual (The Bugle), and a few photographs of campus scenes. A file devoted to the university's War Memorial Hall includes fundraising literature as well as building plans and the building dedication.
The collection also includes a business journal and a daybook, both bearing Perkins's name. The books both contain business transaction entries, and the daybook describes the establishment of the Auburn Bank at Blacksburg in 1894. Rather than detailing actual business transactions, the books were likely used by Perkins for class assignments in bookkeeping. The daybook, for example, includes several pages that are headed "Albany," which contain accounting entries copied verbatim from The New Bryant and Stratton Common School Book-keeping (New York: Ivison, Blakeman, Taylor, 1878). A copy of the November 1904 issue of The Burr McIntosh Monthly completes the collection. The small-format magazine is devoted to photographs of scenery and celebrities of the day.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by document type.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College; Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute
Local Subjects:
University Archives
Contents List
- War Memorial Hall, 1923-1926. (Box-folder 1-1)
- Catalogue of the Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College, 1895. (Box-folder 1-2)
- The Bugle, 1895. (Box-folder 1-3)
- The Bugle, 1898. (Box-folder 1-4)
- Photographs (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Football game in Blacksburg, ca. 1894.
  - Group shoveling deep snow, with rail fence in foreground, ca. 1895.
  - Cadet battalion formation at barracks, ca. 1895.
  - Cadet formation, ca. 1895.
- Business daybook, 1893-1895. (Box-folder 1-6)
- Business journal, 1893-1895. (Box-folder 1-7)
- The Burr McIntosh Monthly, 1904. (Box-folder 1-8)